hello I'm your host David Barnard and my
guest today is Val austino co-founder
and CEO at Monarch money his fifth
startup Val was previously the first
product manager on the original mint.com
team on the podcast I talked with Val
about the importance of passion for the
product you're working on how to
differentiate in a crowded market and
why achieving the viable in minimum
viable product is harder than ever hey
Val thanks so much for joining me on the
podcast today thanks David it's great to
be here I've been meeing you to have you
on for a long time because you and I
spoke gosh like right after I joined
Revenue cat in
2019 yeah it's been a while it has it's
been a while and I've kind of watched
well I became a customer of Monarch
pretty soon after that and so I've
watched the progress from the sidelines
and kept meaning to have you on and then
some big things happened in the fall
we'll get to that yeah it's a great time
to have you on with the recent success
and mint finally shutting down and
that's actually where we wanted to kick
things off so you were at mint for a
while and then after mint you eventually
decided to compete against the old
company that you used to work for to
start things off so many people go build
a meditation app and an already Crow a
category me building a weather up like
an idiot in such a crowded category but
I feel like not too many people think
through deeply like how am I truly going
to differentiate and it seems like the
founding of Monarch was your kind of
recognition that there was a lot more
that you could do with Monarch than was
done at mint so tell me that story of
why you decided to competed against mint
such a behemoth in the industry yeah I
was the first product manager on the
original team that launched mint and
mint was a very fast exit you know from
launch to acquisition was only two years
and what we saw on the product side was
people love seeing all their financial
stuff in one place and mint was kind of
the first online solution to do that of
course quick and you know existed long
before that but you had to manually
enter everything so people loved seeing
everything in one place but then it also
became very evident that tracking and
budgeting just kind of helps you see
what happened in the past and a lot of
people needed help with planning for the
future and understanding their goals and
creating a forecast and historically you
might if you wanted to do that kind of
thing you'd work with a financial
planner but that industry only wants
clients that typically generate three to
$5,000 or more per year in fees and so
it basically prices out about 80% of the
US population so we were thinking about
this back at mint just like hey can we
build a technology or software based
solution to help people with this
financial planning use case it seemed
like that was the obvious next step and
where to go however at the same time our
business model just wasn't working we
were bleeding money many people don't
know this but the aggregation cost of
financial data is very very high so to
have a free product that's paying these
massive fees to the data aggregators we
were basically losing a decent amount of
money on every user and mint was ad
supported but we just weren't making
enough Revenue so we were about to
undergo this kind of pivot and that was
right when in came along and offered to
buy the company and so weade options
there ultimately decided okay this is
probably the best outcome at the time
and then when we got inside of into it
their strategic business case was they
just wanted to funnel folks Into Turbo
Tax which is their big money maker over
time it became pretty clear like there
wasn't much appetite to invest in mint
as a product going forward and so the
whole original mint Team including
myself decided okay this is not really
what we signed on for and most of us
left to go do other things I built and
sold a few other companies But
ultimately felt like someone needs to
come along and continue what we started
it just felt like fundamentally managing
the money for a household is still a
massively unsolved problem and you know
our perspective is budgeting is kind of
like the first step but there's so
things to do after that and honestly
we're just getting started so we've got
a ton of work to do I think we first had
to get to that first level of can we
build a competitive personal finance app
and of course then you also need to do
it across Android and iOS and the web
and so it took us honestly longer to get
there than we thought we didn't plan on
covid we didn't plan on all of the Black
Swan events svb blowing up the market
crashing you know it's been an exciting
few years to be a Founder but yeah the
real Catalyst here here was how do we
actually solve this problem for people
and how do we help them achieve better
Financial outcomes and that can be
defined as whatever is important to you
you know maybe it's getting out of debt
maybe it's buying your first house maybe
it's getting on the same page with your
partner around finances so you stop
fighting about little things like it
means different things for everyone but
our feeling is building sort of a
financial operating system for the
household is kind of the starting point
to get there one of the things you
mentioned in there and it sounds like
this was maybe a point of
differentiation is the business model so
you came out of the gate with Monarch as
a subscription app right and aligned
those incentives a little more directly
instead of taking that ad supported
business model tell me a bit more about
that as part of the foundation of
Monarch as a company and it's kind of a
competitive strategy yeah you know we
didn't think too much about the
competitive differentiation we just sort
of thought about like what do we think
is the right thing to do and you know I
got started in the internet industry in
the late 90s I'm sort of myself here but
I I feel like as an industry we made a
mistake making everything free and AD
supported in the early days and when you
look at a lot of these businesses what
you see over years and if not decades is
they ultimately become their business
model you know like Google and Facebook
are now just ad businesses you know
they're not search businesses they're
not social networks it's their customer
is the advertiser and any kind of AD
supported product you see if it's
successful It ultimately turns into that
and it creates all sorts of societal
issues but it also just creates a shitty
product because you're constantly trying
to drive more and more ad Revenue out of
everything and then people wonder oh why
did this thing get so crappy over time
and I have yet to see an ad supported
product that doesn't have that Arc over
a long period of time conversely when
you look at products and just one more
point on that I think the way we think
of it is direct versus indirect business
models you know like is the end user
paying for it in a direct business model
or an indirect business model you have
some third party AKA The Advertiser
paying for it who by the way is your
real customer under that model and this
was a constant tension it meant you know
it's like how many offers can we get in
front of a user per session like how do
we get them to take things and it was
really at the expense of the user
experience and it was a constant battle
between sort of the revenue team and the
product team and so just as a lifelong
product guy I want to build the best
product we can for our customers and I
love these direct models and especially
subscriptions because it reinforces the
ongoing evolution of the product so you
know huge fans of everything you guys
have built at Revenue cat and what
you're doing with this podcast Foster
that along my feeling is this is really
sort of like a second wave of the
internet there's a whole new approach to
building businesses and building better
products and you look at things you know
like Spotify and du lingo and a lot of
the streaming apps and it's like okay a
people are willing to pay for these now
and I think consumers are sort of waking
up to the the fact like okay if it's ad
supported then they're just after my
attention they're not actually trying to
help or after my data they're not trying
to help me like actually do something
and we're just really religious about
trying to build the best product for the
end user and so it felt obvious that
like a subscription was the right way to
do that yeah I mean I used quickin as a
oneoff purchase and then annual Andor
every couple of years paid upgrade and
then I switched to Mint and I used mint
for a few years probably in those days
when you were still there
it did feel like the product just
stagnated and was just less and less an
enjoyable product it kind of seemed
after the int acquisition to stagnate
and and it kind of makes sense right to
your point it's that I wasn't the
customer I was a
byproduct of into it selling Turbo Tax
which I didn't use and selling ads which
I was not signing up for a bunch of
credit cards and the more profitable
things that I'm sure helped Drive mint
as a business credit card offers and
things like that I wasn't partaking in
those so I was not a good customer then
I started using Monarch a few years ago
and my wife and I love it and you can
tell it's just so different and that's
the thing with the subscription app and
it's not cheap but it's cheap compared
to like you said a financial planner
who's looking to make three or $5,000 on
fees a year it's cheap in the money we
save by actually budgeting and paying
more close attention to our finances and
stuff and in Monarch I definitely feel
like I'm the the customer like you
releasing new features and improving the
app at a pace that it's enjoyable to use
and that's that alignment of business
model with the customer versus the
customer not actually being the customer
in building in a space that was so
mature though what's your view on MVP
especially in regard to such a mature
space like financial planning we had to
build a lot to just get to like the
starting line it felt like in our space
everything's kind of built on top your
data quality and people think oh I'll
just plug in some aggregator and
everything will work and the truth is
you have to add multiple aggregators and
add your own sort of intelligence layer
on top of this to cleanse stuff and so
it was we spent millions of dollars in
years kind of building our own
intelligence layer on top of the
aggregators so that required a bit of
effort but yeah in general you know I
know in startup land we all sort of bow
down to the altar of the MVP and
everything I honestly think the MVP not
just in our category but I'd say most
categories the whole concept of it is
rarely applicable and the reason for
that is you know when a technology is
new like think about when smartphones
were first out right there was like 125
flashlight apps and like 73 fart apps
and everyone was like running around
like look how amazing this is you know I
can like see in the dark and everyone
was kind of trying everything and there
was like this really massive novelty
factor and I think in those early parts
of an industry if you can just get get
something out there and learn like it
makes a lot of sense and people are
trying all these things and there's a
high propensity for novelty and then
folks kind of settle into their habits
and they kind of find their homes and
the data supports this you guys have
been great at sharing a lot of the data
but you can see over the course of years
like people rarely install new apps
these days it's like under 10 I think
whereas it used to be like hundreds in
the early days of the App Store and so
you just see like folks have kind of
solidified on their things and so you
really need to get somebody to change
their behavior or try something new the
bar has gone up much much higher than it
was 10 years ago and that's both
consumers and businesses also and at the
same time there's been this Cambrian
explosion of all these new apps and that
kind of thing and and what you find is
most people just tune it out unless
there's a compelling reason to switch
and it's been interesting to see ai ai
is kind of the new wave right now
there's all this novelty and people are
trying all these different things in AI
but even that like you're starting to
see it sort of Hit the point where folks
like I can't try the latest AI song
generator anymore because I'm bored with
song generators how did you make the
decision at Monarch like what was good
enough for a 1.0 what line did you draw
in the sand of like okay here's what
we're going to release and this would be
too early for us to release it now we
got to wait until we have you know XYZ
featur it's a good question man I still
don't feel like we're at
1.0 we got a lot to do and the good news
for our audience is our customers are
super passionate both positive and
negative so when something breaks or
whatever like we we hear about it so
it's painful for me when we see this
stuff it's like oh my God yes I know we
got to fix that or fix this so we're big
proponents of Rapid feedback from
customers so we really just wanted to
get something out there and kind of
contradicting myself like I wouldn't
have called that necessarily an MVP but
we basically said hey here's where we
are here's the road map that we're
building like we want to do this in
partnership with the audience that are
power user of these types of tools and
so our audience can vote on the Monarch
road map we have you know I think over
15,000 votes on different items and
stuff yeah and many many comments and
people write like dissertations around
their theory of how they budget for this
or that or whatnot and we read through
all that stuff that was kind of our key
was to like get something out there so
we start getting that feedback and we
were in private beta I think for the
first I don't know year or so with a
pretty small group few hundred users and
then we launched in public beta
in early 21 it's kind of been off the
races since then I don't think that's
contradictory I think the standard
thinking of MVP is like get something
super simple and see what works but I
think the key is that the viable part in
minimally viable product the viable has
such a higher bar in 2024 is that what
has traditionally been you know work for
two months and get the MVP out there and
stting getting feedback it's more like
depending on the category and there are
exceptions but that viable part might
actually take a little more time these
days than it ever has in the past yeah
you really have to focus on the customer
job to be done and I think that the jobs
have matured over time you
know that's a good next place to go is
the jobs to be done I know that's
something you think a lot about inside
Monarch how do you apply that jobs to be
done framework in the product building
at Monarch first of all we get the
feedback from customers right we do that
through various mechanisms interviews
survey data our road map comments that I
mentioned so we have a pretty good sense
for what people are trying to achieve
before we ever build something and then
we state it in the sort of jobs to be
done framework of like okay as a
customer what am I hiring this product
to do for me or this feature to do for
me and it's not often what the feature
says on the box it's often you know some
kind of underlying like emotional need
or functional need or whatever and so it
really helps helps us to hypothesize
what those are but then also dig in and
kind of check our assumptions are there
any specific examples from Monarch that
you can site of like here's kind of what
people asked for here's kind of some of
the analysis we did and then here's kind
of the formulation of that jobs to be
done understanding of it and then
contrasting that to like what the
feature says on the tin you know we're
working on one right now which is due
dates on your bills so being able to see
like okay your upcoming bills and the
amounts and all that kind of stuff and
at the outset you'd think okay it's just
I want to pay my bills on time but as we
dig into it we found that and this by
the way this was a feature that mint had
that we did not have in Monarch and then
when a lot of the mint users came over
they've been asking for this so we've
been working on it or pushing it along I
should say since then and we found that
a large part of that audience were folks
that either struggled with ADD and so
like having a single place to see
everything in one spot was like super
valuable and helped them keep everything
up to dat but also another job to be
done is ensuring that you have enough
cash set aside to cover your upcoming
bills right and even what's surprising
about that is it doesn't really matter
what your income or net worth levels are
we see that kind of across different
personas you know a lot of folks are
like hey I've got all these incomings
and outgoings and I just need to make
sure that my balance is map out
correctly at the end of the month or
whatever so you know that's an example
where just listen to what the feature
people are asking for it doesn't get to
some of the more kind of emotional
reasons behind it what are some of the
other ways that you apply jobs to be
done and any other examples that you
have we really start our whole like
product kickoff through that you know so
it's like hey not only do we specify the
jobs to be done but then we like stack
rank them and as a team we try to figure
out what's most important then we will
basically go straight into product specs
and Designs at that point so we
typically create clickable prototypes
and then we'll actually run those by the
customers that voted on a particular
feature so we get the feedback pretty
rapidly like hey is this thing GNA solve
your need or not and so we're able to
iterate again in sort of concert with
our customers in that manner and that's
a big part of our development process
you know honestly it takes longer than
probably the traditional approach but we
feel like you have to do fewer
iterations you've worked on software for
a long time and the classic thing is
like oh get version out there build it
ship it look at the data figure out what
people liked what they didn't like and
then rinse and repeat and that whole
thing just took you three months and
then you're going to do another three
months and finally to get to where
you're trying to get maybe you've spent
nine months in three Rel dot releases on
something whereas if you can do more
upfront iteration it might take you
longer but the end result is better so
let's go through that whole Loop because
I do think more apps could benefit from
this and funny enough I have not seen
this in Monarch so I don't know if it's
only in the beta program or if I just
didn't stumble upon it but first like
what tool do you use and then how do you
expose it to users this whole like
voting on the road map so we use product
board today and it's linked people can
submit requests they can view the road
map it's in our account menu or whatever
so that's the primary mechanism and then
product board makes it easy to reach out
to those individuals and slice and dice
them in different ways and that kind of
thing gotcha okay I'm looking the app
right now and I found it so you have a
row in settings feature requests which
it's kind of a great jobs to be done
analysis of like how do you get somebody
to actually participate in this voting
system and it's like well of course
people want to request a feature and so
you tap on feature request and it takes
you to the product board page where you
see a bunch of ideas up next in progress
and whatnot so you take those ideas you
allow people to vote them up or down and
then and I mean how do you balance like
maybe ones that voted to the top is just
something the team doesn't think it's
the right direction for the product or
like how do you balance the kind of
product intuition against that more
directly building what the users ask and
or doing both at the same time yeah it's
more art than science and it does lead
to some consternation amongst customers
like why why has this thing been on here
so long how come you hav't ship feature
XYZ what's wrong with you people there's
a number of things that dial into it
right it can be often times we're like
hey do we think we can deliver like a
great experience on this you know so
people will often ask for something a
lot of what we do requires data Partners
right and so sometimes we'll spin up
different data Partners we'll run tasks
and we'll just come to the conclusion
like this isn't going to work or it's
not going to be the kind of experience
we want to deliver and so in those cases
we're just like Hey we're g to keep
looking or wait for other data Partners
or try to find other avenues here
sometimes the amount of demand doesn't
jus ify the development effort that
would go into something so it's a
combination of like we have sort of our
strategic road map but we are
opinionated but willing to change our
mind based on customer input so jobs to
be done is helpful and it sounds like
that's kind of a primary framework that
you work through but it doesn't
necessarily handle everything and
there's tons of other product discovery
that you need to do what are some of the
other Frameworks that you use in this
product Discovery and like understanding
what to build for the users we make
pretty heavy use of personas especially
in our category like personal finance is
relevant to everybody technically and
the old like everybody's my Tam but then
but if everybody's your Tam you can't
actually serve everybody so you got to
figure out who you can actually serve
and why yeah yeah that's been honestly
one of the biggest opportunities SL
challenges for us is because people are
so passionate about this you know you
get
like a college student who's really
trying to establish healthy Financial
behaviors but can't imagine why you
would want all these other features and
they're like can't you just give me a
free version that just connects all my
stuff and does exactly what I need and
then you know on the other end of the
spectrum you might have a retiree with
millions of dollars in assets connected
and they want very robust wealth
management and Reporting and that kind
of thing and those are clearly different
use cases but when you dig into it they
all want tracking and budgeting and
automatic classification and net worth
and all this kind of stuff and so yeah
we've had to get very clear on what are
these personas and again it's kind of
like they have different jobs to be done
that so they slot under these personas
and that's been very helpful for us to
decide okay which personas are we
focusing on and going after and what's
the messaging that attracts them and so
on and so forth so that's one the other
is the five y's out of the Toyota
production system made this famous where
they'd have some problem and kind of ask
why and they say ask five times but the
goal is to get to like the root cause
why is something actually broken or
confusing or whatever and if you drill
down five times you'll often get to that
root cause and so this comes back to
that jobs to be done thing you know when
people will often ask oh I want this I
really needed to do XYZ and if you kind
of ask why five times and often it just
takes three you'll come to some sort of
often core emotional problem that
they're trying to solve or tactical
problem or whatever and it gives you
just much better perspective and Clarity
on actually what you're trying to do
wait do you have again another concrete
example of how the five y have helped
kind of dig into a specific need from
the customer this is perhaps not that
surprising but the space we're in a lot
of people say oh I want to see
everything in one place at least at that
personal finance tier that's like one of
the core value props and if you dig into
like what does that get you and people
are often like oh then I can check on
things and I can have some comfort that
I know what what's happening with my
money and so on and so forth and if you
kind of keep like drilling down what you
often find is there's this sense of I
want to be in control humans have like a
need for control and it's this feeling
of order from chaos and that's like a
big emotional driver at that level and I
don't know how many times we had to
double click in there to get that but it
wasn't five it's like probably again
three or so and so that's helped us
realize like okay what are other things
how can we change our messaging and
honestly we haven't done this well
because our team's been so small but now
that we're Staffing up we're going to
lean more into this but you know as you
come up with those things it's like okay
how do we change our marketing to align
with that and so on and so forth
stepping through that let's ask me the
five y so I use Monarch and I like the
view I'm looking at it right now of like
everything in one place and the initial
wise is like yeah it's like why do you
want that well I want to see what's
going on with my finances it's like why
do you want to see what's going on with
your finances well digging into those
wise and like really understanding the
depths of why somebody cares and what
they really care about like having
control of your finances or like
satisfying those anxieties of not having
enough or worrying you're not going to
be able to pay bills or whatever cuz so
often we're tempted to like sell our
product and so like in your product
marketing in your app store screenshots
and everything else you want to show
that view of like all your finances in
one place but what you're selling is not
all your finances in one place what
you're selling is the control the
calming that anxiety and there's a great
illustration I've seen actually Thomas
pedit has this pin do his Twitter that's
where I always go when I want to see it
it's Mario the like little Mario and
then you have the little flower that
Mario gets to be like Mario with the
Fireballs a lot of people like sell the
flower but what you really want to sell
is the badass with the Fireballs
attacking the boss but then what you're
really really selling is like why why do
you want to be the badass with the
Fireballs to save the princess and like
as a marketer you gotta like get down
through those wise to understand what
you're really selling is saving the
princess you're not even selling the
awesome Mario with Fireballs you're
selling Mario actually being able to
save the princess and so it's cool that
yeah as you get through those wise it's
not just about building a better product
but it's actually about better marketing
the product that you've built yep
exactly so next up I wanted to talk
about mint shutting down so we've kind
of been building up to this you were at
mint then Sol the problems at mint you
built Monarch and you've got like a
really deep care for the product and
building something that's really
genuinely helpful to users and you've
been toiling away at this for years I
feel like monarch in your journey is the
perfect example of the saying luck is
when preparation meets opportunity is
that you've been preparing for years
like building this product that you're
passionate about that really serves
users using the job to be done framework
asking the wise and like really building
something and even aligning the business
model with subscriptions and then
announced the shutdown in the fall I
mean it must have just been like insane
moment for y'all as a company so talk me
through like how did you hear and then
like what's happened since yeah it's
been wild and I'll rewind the clock a
little bit and just say that hey we have
been super committed to solving this for
people but like many companies we've
struggled I've been doing this for 20
five years now which is crazy to say out
loud but the last five years have been
the most chaotic with all the Black Swan
events and Co and the things that we
mentioned and so you know as a team we
tried to stay pretty small and control
our destiny like even though we have
raised Venture money we wanted to get to
break even and control our destiny so
we're not constantly on that Loop and so
that was sort of our goal and where we
were headed and then the mint thing hit
and you know we were a small team of
like 13 full-time people and then a
couple outsourced customer support and
then it was just like Off to the Races
our daily sign up rate increased like 20
to 30X overnight and has basically
stayed in that range since then so I'm
not complaining it's been a great
problem to have but we really had to
scramble to add capacity you know to our
database every few hours to we increased
our customer support team from three
people to 20 odd people and of course we
then had the mass massive backlog of Cs
tickets where people are like hating us
because we couldn't get back to them for
days and sometimes weeks it was painful
but now thankfully we're caught up we're
back to our 24-hour response time yeah
we had to scramble quite a bit to take
on the demand so how did you hear about
it like did you saw friends at mint did
you have any idea this was coming or was
it just out of the blue like you're
reading on Twitter the tech Crunch and
you see this article like mint shutting
down mint posted something to their
support Forum saying mint's going away
and we're going to be migrating folks to
Credit Karma but they didn't say when
and of course me and had a pretty active
Reddit community and redditors love to
dig up that kind of stuff so it was sort
of like chumming the water a little bit
and so of course that got picked up and
then we had no idea what was going on
but we already had built a mint importer
and I wrote a blog post that evening
just saying hey as the first product
manager I meant we don't know what's
happening but this is why we think you
should pay for a personal finance
product we've seen how impactful they
are on people's lives we're here to
actually solve this for people and why
you should consider Monarch so I drafted
this blog post that was like October
31st I think and then the next day they
officially announced that they were
going to be shutting it down because it
already I guess come out and so I
revised my blog post pretty quickly we
we posted that and that got picked up on
a number of channels and the press and
that kind of thing and that's sort of
what lit the fuse another great example
of preparation meeting opportunity is
that you were already working on that
blog post based on the rumors that
seemed like something was going on over
at mint so that the blog post was ready
to go that next day when it actually was
announced and getting that kind of
traction that day that it was finally
announced officially that mint was
shutting down was it like all hands on
deck like okay guys this is a big deal
like our business is about to change
to change yeah it was immediately clear
that everything was different like all
of our graphs were up all of our CPU
monitors were going off on our AWS
instance like yeah we scrambled and have
been again we were a small team we only
had five or six Engineers counting my
co-founder at that point and so all
through the holidays like people were
working around the clock and whatnot
they just try and keep even just keeping
the service running in all of that we
only had about an hour and 10 minutes of
downtime it's been five months and we've
upgraded our database six or seven times
we've increased our capacity like we've
had to do all kinds of behind the scenes
things to keep the system running that
doesn't add immediate value to Consumers
and so the downside of some of this is
we've had to push out our traditional
road map in order to add capacity and
also add some of the features like as an
example we did not intend to go into
Canada for some time but there was
enough Canadian Mint users
that were super frustrated M was going
away and there are not really great
Alternatives in Canada and so many of
them were like hacking Monarch and
changing their IP address or whatever in
order to sign up and add Canadian
institutions and we finally just said
okay we're going to turn this on and
kind of beta and see what happens and
it's been you know honestly it's been a
little bit of a mixed bag Canadian
institutions do not have the same data
connectivity that American institutions
have and so we've had some frustrated
Canadian customers and we just offer
them a refund and a lot of them are
happy but that's a good example of
something that like wasn't even on our
plan for the next 12 months but it
became immediately clear like this is an
opportunity to do something here I'm
glad we did it but we definitely have to
add more support for Canadian
institutions which we're working on how
has it been positioning yourself against
other competitors when a Black Swan
event like this comes along like people
listening to this podcast may never run
into something like this but they may
and like in the weather category like
last year year a lot of apps saw a huge
influx when Apple weather went down
there are these times when things like
this happen when I mean covid right like
all these fitness apps needing to switch
to at home workouts and a lot of apps
blew up during covid they weren't
expecting the kind of hockey stick
growth you know you go viral David Smith
went viral with Widget Smith although
it's not necessarily going to happen to
a large percentage of the people
listening if something like this happens
to somebody else any kind of advice and
how have you looked to like best
leverage this while just trying to keep
the wheels on the bus I think what we've
been pretty good at is when something
like this happens you kind of have to
just stop yourself and say okay like
what does the new reality look like and
divorce yourself from like your previous
decisions and folks often have the sunk
cost and like oh wait we've already
decided we're going to do XYZ and we've
told people we're doing XYZ and it's
really hard to like we had promised a
few big features to our user base and a
lot of folks are still waiting for some
of these things like we're overhauling
our goals feature which is our whole
like planning engine and it's a massive
project and we basically just had to put
that on hold and say we've got to do
this infrastructure work we've got to
like support these mint users we've
gotta and in doing so it's going to get
us the revenue and the resources to do
these other things you know but we
basically had to really stop doing
everything that we had told our
investors and our customers and
everything else that we were going to do
and just decide okay starting now what
are the most important things going
forward and how do we stack rank these
and how quickly can we get on it and
like we upgraded our Chrome extension
because it was having some issues with
capacity and we got you know a whole new
Chrome extension out in like 48 Hours
whereas some of our peers started
working on this when it happened and it
took them six weeks or longer to get an
import thing launched and so it's a
combination I think of having a the
talent the team that's able to move
quickly B the sort of urgency and the
wherewithal to make those decisions and
just get aligned as a group and that's
you know when good stuff happens it was
the same thing when svb went down and we
were banking with Silicon Valley Bank it
was like holy maybe we're dead
maybe we're not we don't know and we had
to scramble to like get other lines of
capital in place like pretty quickly
just as like a back stop in case
something happened wow so you had two
black swans in the same year so that was
March no it's been yeah it's been while
we had obviously covid but then a lot of
our team our team's remote in California
and the Pacific Northwest mostly
we had a lot of folks displaced with
fires we had folks this is going back a
few years with a lot of this sort of
social unrest and Seattle and Portland
disrupted folks obviously the market
totally course correcting and so on and
so forth ATT rolling out there's a lot
of these things that were existential
that have been pretty big blips so the
mint shutdown was the first one that was
positive so I think we've earned
it again preparation meeting opportunity
you kind of had fought a lot of fires
and had to I like that too talking about
like speed of execution is that you can
build that muscle so that when an
opportunity does present itself the team
is ready to capitalize on it and to move
quickly and then that's just a good
muscle to build anyway as a product team
to be able to move quickly and build and
iterate how have you thought about
positioning and capitalizing as much as
you can on this transition away from
mint you know is there specific
marketing and other things that you've
done to maximize this opportunity I'm
sure we haven't maximized it as much as
we can we didn't really have a marketing
team when this happened we were sort of
the founders we're kind of doing it
ourselves and since then we've been
bringing people on board and building
out that team so I think on the
marketing side and of course we're
working with agencies and stuff so we
probably undere executed there but what
we did do well was we really
communicated with the mint folks
primarily through Reddit and just said
hey like here's kind of our philosophy
like this is why we're doing it like
we're in it for the Hall our goal is to
like actually solve this problem for
people and we acknowledge like we're
just getting started even though we're 5
years into this there's institutions
that are still flaky there's features
that we need to add we're kind of 20%
into our journey if that and so we've
got a long road map of stuff to build
and I think people like that okay these
folks sound authentic they sound like
they're here to like actually listen to
us and build it and that I think for at
least that audience who by the way you
got to remember they just felt like they
got screwed over by one of their apps in
some cases so there was a lot of
emotional drive to find something new
that they felt like they could trust
yeah the trust is a big thing again like
if you ask the wise why are you
switching for mint well mint's shutting
down okay well what are you looking for
in the new product and like why Monarch
versus the competitors like mint you
said was automatically trying to
transition some people to another tool
yeah you can into it bot Credit Karma
and if you look out to that lens there
decision made sense you know Credit
Karma had hundreds of millions of users
and was generating billions of dollars
in ad Revenue mint was losing money so
they were kind of like hey we'll just I
can see the meeting now they're probably
like why is this thing even here let's
turn it off and just push those people
into Credit Karma and of course Credit
Karma doesn't do a lot of the personal
finance stuff and so I'm sure many
people moved over and some people are
probably happy but a lot of people are
not so that was their transition plan
and so yeah we kind of just said hey
here's what Monarch does and here's what
we're and I think that help people feel
comfortable there what's next for
Monarch money in the company building
not in the product I think a lot of our
listeners are more interested in what's
next strategically what's next in
building out the company what's next in
marketing and things like that yeah so
first and foremost we're leveraging the
revenue and new user base to staff up
like very dramatically so that we can
really just invest more in product
development so we have about 20 five
roles we're recruiting for right now I
mean most of those are engineering
product design so if anyone's listening
to this you can apply on our website if
you're interested in this space that's
the main thing and then obviously that
translates into just more road map and
building here we are also investing in
marketing but specifically in content
and so our feeling has always been that
to solve this problem for people yes you
need like a product and a tool but you
also need some of Education to help
folks understand some of these Concepts
it's really a shame that we go through
our school system in this country and
you learn stuff like photosynthesis
that's important but it's not something
you really need every day whereas things
you know like how credit cards work no
one's ever taught this until they
oftentimes run into credit card debt and
then get themselves in trouble and are
like oh my gosh I need to do something
different here so our hope is that we
can provide sort of the missing personal
finance course that people should get in
high school or college and just help
teach folks those Basics so we're
building out that team currently so
we've talked a lot about Monarch the
product and product thinking and where
you're headed but since this all
happened in the fall you must be putting
in a lot of 80h hour weeks or maybe more
than 80 hour weeks what's the why for
you like we've talked about the five
wise of asking good product questions
but there's also the wies of building a
company and running a business and
caring enough to do those 80h hour weeks
what are your wise I mean I guess
personally I've felt this pain pretty
acutely as a Founder I you know this
right you go through periods where you
basically pay yourself nothing and so
it's an emotional roller coaster even
and then you add on like the financial
roller coaster on top of it so I always
had my own spreadsheets and models and
all that kind of stuff that I would use
to try and figure out okay is our family
going to be okay and we made the
decision when my kids were young that my
wife would stay home and do that
primarily and we were living in the Bay
Area so here we were like a family of
five on a Founder salary just basically
bleeding money every month and so I was
very intently kind of watching
everything and using all of these
products and that's ultimately like when
I landed at mint so there's that
personal level then when I was at mint I
saw
firsthand how much people just struggle
with finances when you dig into the
research finances are the number one
source of stress in American families
it's the number one cause of divorce
it's one of primary causes of like
depression and suicide not even getting
into some of the societal inequity stuff
and you realize like another truism that
most people don't know is that Financial
Health is actually more a function of
behavior than it is your income and it's
kind of like physical health in that way
you know if you can be consistent about
walking a little bit every day you're
going to be in a much healthier position
than if you try to run a marathon once
every five years for example and it's
the same with finances if you do like
the Small Things day in and day out you
will ultimately be successful or
financially healthy I should say so
those were some of like the learnings
along the way and honestly I don't know
that I would have picked that up had I
not been at mint and done so many
customer interviews and so on the one
hand it was like here we have this acute
pain and problem and we were felt to me
like we were just getting started and
then all of a sudden it stopped it was
like okay the train tracks just ended or
the bridge ended and I was like we got
to finish the bridge we haven't crossed
over this River yet or whatever this
analogy I'm putting together here means
and our team is just very passionate
about that everyone on the team has a
similar story about growing up in
financially constrained homes or
challenges on this and so many of them
have come at it from different angles
and it makes us I think pretty
empathetic group it's great to like work
on something that you can see firsthand
I mean we get hundreds a week of people
emailing us and just being like Oh my
gosh my husband or my wife and I are no
longer fighting about money or can walk
into a grocery store and not have a
panic attack about bouncing a check
because I know how much cash I have and
you start to realize like the real
impact these types of things have on
people's lives so it's very rewarding
and like I said it feels like we're just
kind of getting started here I think
that's a good point too in product
building generally and then startups
more specifically is that if you're
going to go build an app you don't care
about and then think about working on
that for the next 10 years of your life
it's really great to hear the passion
that you have for it I'm sure that helps
kind of Drive sticking it out through
those hard times I mean yeah there's a
ton of up and down in startups as you
know I'm assuming most your audience
does as well and YC has this famous
saying like startups die for two reasons
like they either run out of money or the
founders quit and everyone thinks it's
mostly the money part but when you get
behind the scenes you realize like a lot
of companies just die because the
founding team is like I don't want to do
this anymore you know it's too painful I
don't believe in it we're not having fun
not that they're really fun to begin
with but you know what I
mean don't start a start up because you
think it's going to be F exactly so I
always tell entrepreneurs try and pick a
problem that you want to work on for 10
years even if it were to fail and that's
kind of how I feel like even if Monarch
were to fail I would feel good that we
like move the ball forward we did
something we helped people along the way
and so on and so forth you know I think
if you use that litmus test it quickly
filters out a lot of companies that you
might start where you're like okay would
I do this if I knew I wasn't ever GNA
like have an exit and I don't know I
think that's a good elus test for what
you should work on well I think that's a
really great place to wrap it up so I
was looking for you online and was going
to you know link like I typically do to
Twitter and Linkedin and all that but
you're a hard man to find online I am
online I have a Twitter and Linkedin
profile I will say that I spend very
little time on social media by Design
I've got three kids
I take care of my aging mom who has
dementia and then of course I'm running
Monarch so all my time goes into those
three things but if you want to DM me on
Twitter I will see that and I may
respond and I may
not great way to put it um no you've got
a lot going on maybe we won't link to
your your Twitter or LinkedIn F it's
okay but I did want to say I think the
most interesting things folks can get in
touch with and you kind of touched on
this already is that monarch is growing
like crazy and needs good people you
mentioned already of 20 something job
posting any specific ones you want to
call out for this audience Engineers
obviously we've got multiple product
manager roles marketing roles and the
other thing I'll say is we do have just
a open role or future opportunities and
we've hired a lot of folks through that
where they're like hey I don't see
something that matches what I'm doing
but I love what you guys are up to and
I'd love to be a part of this and I'd
say nearly half of our team has kind of
comes through that Avenue so if you
don't see something on there but you're
excited about this or just want to get
in touch like please don't let that stop
you cool and then the best way for that
is to not DM is to actually go ahead and
fill out the
form the right people Monarch money
thinkc careers and you can see them all
listed there awesome well Val it's been
so fascinating and congrats on all the
success post mint shut down and congrats
for building a great product like my
wife and I use it and my wife and I
never like fought over money but I will
say a job to be done for me of Monarch
money is when my wife is like we don't
talk enough or like I don't know what's
going on with their finances I'm just
like sweetie lug into Monarch like it's
all there I I keep track and like our
budgets there and like our investment
accounts are
there so that used to be your thing is
like you don't ever tell me about what's
going on with the money I'm like it's
all there look you have a log in go look
awesome well I'm glad it's working for
you guys and yeah thank you for being a
a customer and a Advocate awesome thanks
so much Val you bet take
care thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. subclub do.com to
join our private community
[Music]